Guide to the Russell Lynes Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Russell Lynes papers
1939-1991
YCAL MSS 553
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
45
(44 boxes)
The Russell Lynes papers contain material documenting the career and personal life of American author and editor Russell Lynes. The collection contains writings, correspondence, photographs, and personal and family papers. Early gifts from Russell Lynes consist chiefly of writings, including drafts, setting copies, and proofs for works of the period, such as The Tastemakers (1954), A Surfeit of Honey (1957), Cadwallader (1959), The Domesticated Americans (1963), and Good Old Modern (1973). Later acquistions also contain writings, with some additional drafts for book-length works, though chiefly shorter works, as well as correspondence, photographs, and personal and family papers.
Lynes, Russell, 1910-1991
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Russell and Mildred Lynes, 1958-1993.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Russell Lynes (1910-1991)
Russell Lynes, born Joseph Russell Lynes, Jr. on 2 December 1910 in Great Barrington, Massachusetts, was an American art historian, photographer, author and managing editor of Harper's magazine. Lynes may be best remembered for his satirical commentary on American tastes and mores. In early works such as Highbrow, Lowbrow, Middlebrow (1949), Snobs (1950), and The Tastemakers (1954), Lynes mocked what he considered to be Americans' questionable preferences in art and architecture. Other works include Guests (1951), The Domesticated Americans (1963), and The Art-Makers of Nineteenth Century America (1970). Lynes died on 14 September 1991 in New York City.
Biographical information taken from "(Joseph) Russell (Jr.) Lynes." Contemporary Authors Online. Detroit: Gale, 2000. Gale Biography In Context. Web. 29 Feb. 2012.
Scope and Contents
The Russell Lynes papers contain material documenting the career and personal life of American author and editor Russell Lynes. The collection contains writings, correspondence, photographs, personal and family papers. Early gifts from Russell Lynes consist chiefly of writings, including drafts, setting copies, and proofs for works of the period, such as The Tastemakers (1954), A Surfeit of Honey (1957), Cadwallader (1959), The Domesticated Americans (1963), and Good Old Modern (1973). Later acquistions also contain writings, with some additional drafts for book-length works, though chiefly shorter works, as well as correspondence, photographs, and personal and family papers.
Arrangement
Organized into thirteen groupings: 1958 Acquisition, 1959 Acquisition, 1960 Acquisition, 1961 Acquisition, 1962 Acquisition, 1967 Acquisition, 1973 Acquisition, 1976 Acquisition, 1977 Acquisition, 1980 Acquisition, 1981 Acquisition, 1992 Acquisition (Uncat Za Ms 253), and 1993 Acquisition (Uncat Za Ms 277).
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Lynes, Russell, 1910-1991
- 1958 Acquisition, 1952-1957; Series I; 3
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Scope and Contents
  Former call number: Za Lynes.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Russell Lynes.
  - A Surfeit of Honey, setting copy and galley proof, [1957]; 2 (Box 1)
  - The Upper Bohemian, draft, 1952 (Box 1)
- 1959 Acquisition, Series II; 2
  - Cadwallader, setting copy and proof, 1959; 2 (Box 1)
- 1960 Acquisition, 1935-1959; Series III; 3
  - Correspondence, 1939-1959 (Box 1)
  - Measures for Song and Dance by Katherine Anne Porter, poem, typescript, corrected, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Reading list for the English classes, 1939, undated (Box 1)
- 1961 Acquisition, [circa 1950]; Series IV
  - Snobs, draft, [circa 1950] (Box 2)
- 1962 Acquisition, 1952; Series V
  - Bibliography of "books, articles, essays, etc." by Lynes, holograph, photocopy, 1952 June 26 (Box 2)
- 1967 Acquisition, [1954]-1963; Series VI; 7
  - The Domesticated Americans, setting copy, [1963]; 3 (Box 2)
  - The Domesticated Americans, galley proofs, 1963; 2 (Box 3)
  - The Tastemakers, setting copy, [circa 1954]; 2 (Box 4)
- 1973 Acquisition, undated; Series VII
  - "150 Billion Green Stamps and What They Can Get You," galley proof Good Old Modern, undated (Box 4)
- 1976 Acquisition, undated; Series VIII; 4
  - Good Old Modern, draft, corrected, undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - Good Old Modern, draft, corrected, undated; 2 (Box 5)
- 1977 Acquisition, 1972-1973; Series IX
  - Material relating to the Edward MacDowell Medal given to Norman Mailer, 1972-1973 (Box 5)
- 1980 Acquisition, Series X; 16
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - List of correspondents
    - Auden, W. H. (Box 5)
    - Berman, Eugene (Box 5)
    - Forster, E. M. (Box 5)
    - Huxley, Aldous (Box 5)
    - Koestler, Arthur (Box 5)
    - Lancaster, Osbert (Box 5)
    - Moore, Marianne (Box 5)
    - Mortimer, Raymond (Box 5)
    - Porter, Katherine Anne (Box 5)
    - Pritchett, Victor and Dorothy (Box 5)
    - Read, Sir Herbert (Box 5)
    - Toynbee, Arnold (Box 5)
    - Welty, Eudora (Box 5)
    - West, Jessamyn (Box 6)
    - West, Rebecca (Box 6)
    - Woodham-Smith, Cecil (Box 6)
- 1981 Acquisition, 1952-1981; Series XI; 23
  - "A Very Long Letter to Liz From Her Father Russell Lynes, September 21, 1976 -- December 16, 1979," typescript, photocopy, 1981; 22 (Box 6)
  - The Tastemakers, outline, 1952 June 11 (Box 6)
    Includes letters from Lynes dated 1948 and 1981
- 1992 Acquisition, 1940-1991; Series XII; (29 boxes)
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 253.
  Gift of Mildred Lynes.
  - Art Forgeries (Box 7)
  - C/A Financial & Legal - 1980 (Box 7)
  - After Hours Subjects (Box 7)
  - Metropolitan Museum - American 19th Century, Symposium - 1970 (Box 7)
  - Bryant, National Council on the Arts (Box 7)
  - Hyatt Mayor (Box 7)
  - Crawford, Ralston (Box 7)
  - C-H piece on Changing Taste (Box 7)
  - Columbia Journalism Review (Box 7)
  - Digressionists (Box 7)
  - San Francisco - Misc. (Box 7)
  - American Academy in Rome (Box 7)
  - Venice 1971 (Box 7)
  - Atlanta (Box 7)
  - Houghton, Arthur Q., Jr. (Box 7)
  - Houston, James (Box 7)
  - Thanotology Symposium (Box 7)
  - R.L. Exhibition (Box 7)
  - New Orleans (Box 7)
  - Archives for Smithsonian (Box 7)
  - AAR Exhibit (Box 7)
  - CUNY (L.H.D '80) (Box 7)
  - Artists' Fellowship Medal 1981 (Box 7)
  - Bugatti (Box 7)
  - Russell Wright (Box 7)
  - Skowhegan (Box 7)
  - Lively Audience (Box 7)
  - Art in America (Box 7)
  - The White House - 1981 (Box 7)
  - Innovative Furniture (Box 7)
  - Vanderlyn - At the Met (Box 7)
  - Cooper-Hewitt or Arch. Digest '83 (Box 7)
  - Untitled (Box 7)
  - Untitled (Box 7)
  - After Hours 1970 (Box 7)
  - After Hours 1969 (Box 7)
  - After Hours 1968 (Box 7)
  - After Hours 1967 (Box 7)
  - After Hours 1966 (Box 7)
  - Mildred Akin Lynes MA certificate from NYU, 1940 June (Box 8)
  - The Lively Audience, top copy (Box 8)
  - The Domesticated Americans (Box 8)
  - Poster for Russell Lynes lecture, [circa 1961] (Box 8)
  - Confessions of a Dilettante (Box 9)
  - Color slides, 2 (Box 9)
  - R. L. C/A Honorary Member 1981 (Box 9)
  - Alfred H. Barr, Jr. misc pieces (Box 9)
  - The Cult of the West (Box 9)
  - Osborn, R. & E. (Box 10)
  - O miscl. (Box 10)
  - Rome - 1981 (Box 10)
  - Reed, Henry Hope (Box 10)
  - Ritchie, Andrew and Jane (Box 10)
  - Royal Society of Arts (Box 10)
  - Russell, John (Box 10)
  - R miscl. (Box 10)
  - RL miscl. (Box 10)
  - Hewitt - Mr. & Mrs. Abram S. Notes (empty) (Box 10)
  - Brinelleschi- (empty) (Box 10)
  - C.-H. Victoria & Albert Exhibition (empty) (Box 10)
  - C.-H. Decorative Arts Colls. (empty) (Box 10)
  - Exhib: "Man Transforms" 1976 (empty) (Box 10)
  - C.-H. - Outlines (empty) (Box 10)
  - Cooper-Hewitt repairs to make etc. (empty) (Box 10)
  - Presto Pino (Box 10)
  - Photo Expenses 1984-87 (Box 10)
  - Plimpton, Francis T.P. (Box 10)
  - Pritchett, V.S. (Box 10)
  - Portugal (Box 10)
  - Possible Magazine Projects (Box 10)
  - P miscl. (Box 10)
  - Permissions (Box 10)
  - RL & Mal Passports (Box 10)
  - Park-McCullough House (Box 10)
  - Perlin, Bernard (Box 10)
  - N.-Y.H.S. (Box 10)
  - N.-Y.H.S. Museum Com. (Box 10)
  - New York Times (Box 10)
  - N miscl. (Box 10)
  - National Gallery of Art (Box 10)
  - National Museum of Amer. Art (Washington) (Box 10)
  - Needle Point (Box 10)
  - Nat'l Ac of Design (John Dobkin) (Box 10)
  - Nat'l Academy of Design (Short History by RL - in both English and Italian) (Box 10)
  - Maryland Institute College of Art - Baltimore (Box 10)
  - Melchert, James (AAR) (Box 10)
  - Met. Bryant Fellows (Box 10)
  - "Architects At Work," Journal of the American Institute of Architecture, August 1951 (Box 11)
  - Archives of American Art (Box 11)
  - Art and the Affluent Society - Canadian Art Sept./Oct. 1961 (a speech at the Canadian Conference of the Arts, Toronto)(empty) (Box 11)
  - The Artist as Uneconomic Man, Saturday Review, Feb. 28 '70 (Box 11)
  - ARTnews "1902" Nov. 1987 (Box 11)
  - "The Arts Look Lively in Boston" Collier's June 22, 1956 (Box 11)
  - "The Art of Accepting" Vogue, Sept. 1, 1952 (Box 11)
  - Beaux Arts at the Modern (Smithsonian, Nov. 1975) (Box 11)
  - Bad Taste, Good Taste, Distaste, Show, Dec 1963 (Box 11)
  - "Be Glad You're Middle-Aged", Hook, Feb 21, 1956 (Box 11)
  - Best Sellers of the 1950s, for the New York Times Book Review Nov 1959 (Box 11)
  - Bermuda Bryson: Illustrator, Print Vol x #1 (Box 11)
  - "Bone Bank", Harper's April 1948 (Box 11)
  - "Bores" (Box 11)
  - Bowling Goes Bourgeois, Harijon, March 1963 (Box 11)
  - Bryant, "Countryman-poet let some fresh air into old New York" (Box 11)
  - Confessions of an Author-Editor (Box 11)
  - Can the Private Schools Survive? (Box 11)
  - Clothes Make What Man?, Cosmopolitan Mag., March 1969 (Box 11)
  - "The Buick in the Snow" (unpublished, written for Harper's, see notes) (Box 11)
  - The Delightful Privincialism of Portugal - Harper's Mag., Nov. '65 (Box 11)
  - Culture-Struck Canada, Harper's, August 1961 (Box 11)
  - Cooper-Hewitt Museum "A brief Cooper-Hewitt History", Cooper-Hewitt Newsletter Vol 5, No 1. Fall 1981 (Box 11)
  - Cooper-Hewitt And Its Concern for American Taste, Smithsonian, Nov. 1977 (Box 11)
  - A Cool Cheer for Middle-Age, Look, Oct. 17, 1967 (Box 11)
  - Confessions of A Needle Pointer, House Beautiful, Nov. 1966 (Box 11)
  - "Every Day a New Picasso", Look, Jan 10, 1956 (Box 11)
  - Everything's Up-to-Date in Texas...But Me, Harper's, May 1961 (Box 11)
  - The Erosion of Detroit, Harper's, Jan 1960 (Box 11)
  - Emphatic Istanbul, Harper's Magazine, Nov. 1964 (Box 11)
  - Dossena, "Forgery for Fun & Profit", "After Hours" - Harper's Mag, Feb 1968 (Box 11)
  - Does Your Bathroom Give You Away?, Home & Garden, July 1958 (Box 11)
  - "Desire Out From Under the Elms," Harper's Magazine, July 1957 (Box 11)
  - The Gay, Gaudy History of the American Bedroom...And Bath, McCall's, Oct 1963 (Box 11)
  - "The Gay Blades", Mademoiselle, Jan 1956 (Box 11)
  - "Gaudy to Drab to Gaudy" (Harper's) (Box 11)
  - Piece for "House & Garden" ("Forget them Never") (Box 11)
  - Four Critics in Search of an Answer, pub. in the book Advertising Directions 2, 1961 (Box 11)
  - Folly Forgiven, or Xmas is for Beginners, Mademoiselle, Dec. 1963 (Box 11)
  - A Fly-by-night Trip to Morocco, Harper's August 1963 (After Hours) (Box 11)
  - The Finest Rooms - Introduction, pub. Viking Press 1964 (Box 11)
  - "The Fine Edge of Awareness", Good Housekeeping, May 1960 (Box 11)
  - Fallon Piece - Oct. 4, 1959 (Box 11)
  - "Executive View" Review of exhibition, "Art in America", Spring 1957 (Box 11)
  - Everything You Need to Know About Taste (Box 11)
  - The Genteel Tradition, American Art Journal, Nov. '74 (Box 11)
  - The Gentle Tyranny of Books, House Beautiful, May 1969 (Box 11)
  - Goodbye to World's Fans, Harper's Magazine, Oct. 1965 (After Hours) (Box 11)
  - Good Corn - Bad Corn (Box 11)
  - "Government as a Patron of the Arts", Yale Review - Autumn 1952 (Box 11)
  - Grand Rapids, "The Treatment", Harper's Mag., Jan 1962 (Box 11)
  - Great-Grandfather's Table, Antiques World, Sept. 1980 (Box 11)
  - Green Stamps, 150 Billion, World Magazine, 12/19/72 (Box 11)
  - "Hands Off the Birds",Woman's Day, Nov. 1952 (Box 11)
  - "Have a Good Cry", House Beautiful, June 1956 (Box 11)
  - John Held's Mad World (Box 11)
  - Highbrow, Lowbrow, Middlebrow (Box 11)
  - Hirshhorn Museum - Smithsonian, Dec. '74 & Jan. '75 (Box 11)
  - Hoving, "A Conversation with Mr. Hoving" for Art in America, 1967 (Box 11)
  - How America Invented Manners, Saturday Evening Post. Dec. 22-29, '62 (Box 11)
  - How Do You Rate in the New Leisure Chart - Life, Dec. 29. '59 (Box 11)
  - How America "Solved" the Servant Problem, Harper's, July 1963 (Box 11)
  - How Good are the Junior Colleges?, Harper's Magazine, Nov. 1966 (Box 11)
  - How Not to Build a Pond, Country Journal, Aug. '74 (Box 11)
  - How Shoe Can You Get?, Esquire, Sept. 1953 (Box 11)
  - How to Tell Men Apart, McCall's - January 1956 (Box 11)
  - How TV is Changing Us (or the Electronic Express), TV Guide, Feb 24, '68 (Box 11)
  - How the Mus. of Modern Art Survived the Fire, from Good Old Modern, Smithsonian, May 1973 (Box 11)
  - Husbands: the New Servant Class, Look, December 14, 1954 (Box 11)
  - "Independence of Ugliness" AIA Conference, Hotel Plaza, Apr. 3, 1962 (Box 11)
  - An Invitation to the Ball, Family Circle Magazine (Box 11)
  - "I Want to Be Creative...or Something", Mademoiselle, Nov. 1951 (Box 11)
  - Intellectual Snobs, Cosmopolitan, January 1957 (Box 11)
  - Intellectuals vs. Philistines (New York Times Book Review), July 10, 1949 (Box 11)
  - Is Kindness Killing the Arts?, Harper's Magazine, Nov. 1963 (Box 11)
  - Is There a Lady in the House?, Look (Box 11)
  - Is There a Gentlemen in the House?, Look, June 9, 1959 (Box 11)
  - "Highbrow, Lowbrow, Middlebrow", correspondence (Box 11)
  - "Italy: Once Over Lightly", Harper's, Feb. 1952 (Box 11)
  - Vassar Alumnae Mag., Oct. 1948 (Box 11)
  - John Kouwenhoven Artsletter, Vermont Council on the Arts, Nov-Dec '82 (Box 11)
  - "Look Out for Falling Angels", Harper's May-Feb 1972 (Box 11)
  - The Lost Art of Doing Nothing (written for Country Beautiful, Jan. 1962) (Box 11)
  - Luman Reed - (Apollo Magazine, London Feb. '78) written for American Magazine, 1977 (Box 11)
  - "The Making of a Modern Museum", Arts Magazine, Feb. 1980, Cooper-Hewitt (Box 11)
  - Harper's Aug., 1954 (Box 11)
  - Hyatt Mayor, ARTnews, Summer 1980, vol. 79, no. 6 (Box 11)
  - "A Man Has the last Word", Look, Oct. 16, 1956 (Box 11)
  - Men, Manners, and Matrimony, Charm, January 1959 (Box 11)
  - Middle Age - notes etc., Look Magazine, Oct. 17, 1967 (Box 11)
  - Lists of RL articles (Box 12)
  - The Age of Taste (Box 12)
  - American Academy in Rome - A Perspective - Rome 1981 (Box 12)
  - The American at Home - 1957, Architecture Record, Spring 1957 (Box 12)
  - American Manners 1856-1956 (Box 12)
  - The American Nesting Instinct - N.Y. Times Magazine supplement on "The Home" 29 Sept. '74 (Box 12)
  - "The American Spaceman", Western World, June 1957 (Box 12)
  - "The Archives of American Art", Art & Antiques, Jan/Feb '80 (Box 12)
  - Architects in Glass House, correspondence and clippings (Box 12)
  - "Architects Uneasy Peace" Architectural Forum" May 1955 (Box 12)
  - [Loose material] (Box 12)
  - RL-Personal - 1960 (Box 12)
  - RL-Personal - 1962 (Box 12)
  - Russell Lyons- Personal - 1956 (Box 12)
  - Snobs correspondence (Box 12)
  - Lynes Personal 1955 (Box 12)
  - Russell Lyons correspondence 1960 (Box 12)
  - RL Personal 1961 (Box 12)
  - No. Adams State - commencement 28 May '77 (Box 13)
  - Soc. of American Historians - talk about the century at dinner 5/6/75 (Box 13)
  - Pintard Meeting - N.Y. Historical Soc. 17 Oct. '74 (Box 13)
  - Notes on The Genteel Tradition, Univ. of Delaware Symposium Apr. 19, 1974 (Box 13)
  - Maryland Institute commencement address 1973 (Box 13)
  - Goucher College commencement 1966 (Box 13)
  - Commencement speech R.I.S.D. June 1, 1957 (Box 13)
  - Talk for the Union Club - Oct. 17, '73 and Cosmopolitan Club Jan 16. '74 (Box 13)
  - Lecture for U. of Kansas Art Museum Nov. 1972 (Box 13)
  - The Museum of Modern Art and Architecture in the 1930s - College Art Association, January 25, 1973 (NYC) (Box 13)
  - Who Wants Art - Lecture for UCSB, 26 Feb. '70 (Box 13)
  - The State of the Arts - Lecture for Notre Dame Contemporary Arts Festival, Apr. 17, 1969 (Box 13)
  - "Sense & Nonsense About Mass Culture", speech for Michigan Literary Association (Box 13)
  - "The Persistence of American Taste", lecture for Detroit Institute of Art, Oct 20, 1959 (Box 13)
  - "From Limner to Tastemaker", lecture for Met. Museum Symposium, May 2, '70 (Box 13)
  - MacDowell Colony Benefits 1956, 1966 (Box 13)
  - "Design for Washington", Governor's conference on Dec. 3, 1965 (Box 13)
  - Talk for the Cathedral Choir School - Feb. 13, 1966 (Box 13)
  - New Members Dinner, Century Assn., Nov '68 (Box 13)
  - Shipley Conference - Apr 1, '66 "The Editor and the Young Writer" (Box 13)
  - The Climate of Art Patronage Today, lecture, Yale Sch. of Art & Architecture, Oct. 21, 1964 (Box 13)
  - Speech for "Book & Author" lunch - Washington D.C., October 22, 1963 (Box 13)
  - Mass Culture and Snobbery - for Symposium at Brandeis University, June 2, 1962 (Box 13)
  - A.L.H. Transportation Conference, Williamsburg, Va., Feb. 9, 1967 (Box 13)
  - The Footloose Americans at Home, Lecture given at N.Y. Historical Soc., May 1964 (Box 13)
  - Talk on Being an Editor and Author - several versions (Box 13)
  - Pillsbury Co. Talk - 4/17/67 (Box 13)
  - "Aesthetics & the City", Regional Plan Assoc. Conference - Nov. 9, 1964 (Box 13)
  - Talk for NSID Lunch - Apr. 29, '64 and revision for AIA Chicago - Jan 7, '65 (Box 13)
  - Speech - Cincinnati Museum of Art, October 3, 1955 (Box 13)
  - Lecture for Cooper Union, "the Forgotten Pedestrian", Feb. 21, 1956 (Box 13)
  - Speech for Cleveland AIA, Jan. 24, 1962, on "Mobility" (Box 13)
  - Mobility and Design - Lecture for Harvard School of Design (Box 13)
  - Speech for Am. Assoc. of Junior Colleges - St. Louis, March 3, '66 (Box 13)
  - Fast Food & Quickbed Conference, Abbey Hotel, Wisconsin, 1965 (Box 13)
  - American Institute of Decorators - Speech, April 5, 1950, Sept. 1955 (Box 13)
  - Collegiate School commencement 1965 (Box 13)
  - Memo for N.B.C. TV "Projects" on Beautiful Women, 9/20/60 (Box 13)
  - "What the Whirlwind Blew Away" lecture for 1963 Armory Show, April 18, '63, given at the 26th St. Armory (Box 13)
  - Speech for Amer. Federation of Art, 1948 (Box 13)
  - Union College Convocation, Feb. 25, 1964 (Box 13)
  - Armory Show Lecture - April 18, 1963, given at the 69th Reg. Armory (Box 13)
  - "The Nation's Future" - transcript of TV debate, Prof. J.K. Galbraith & R.L., Feb. 11, 1961 - N.B.C. TV. (empty) (Box 13)
  - "The Image of the Intellectual", lecture prepared for Bryn Mawr College - April 1961 (Box 13)
  - Talk for the Publishers and Club, Dec. 10, 1954 (Box 13)
  - Speech for American Booksellers Assn., Washington, June 15, 1959 (Box 13)
  - Lecture for Corcoran Gallery, Washington - Nov. 1, 1955 (Box 13)
  - Talk for TV-Show "Comment", 6/19/55 (Box 13)
  - Steinberg Speech - Richmond, VA, Nov. 27, 1953 (Box 13)
  - Fashion Group - Speech - 1949 (empty) (Box 13)
  - Speech for Nat'l Assn. of College Stores Book & Author lunch, May 1965 (Box 13)
  - Notes for Talk at Berkeley College, Feb. 1960, "A Journalist's View of American Society" (Box 13)
  - Speech for AIR. New York - March 23, 1955, excerpt printed in Architectural Forum - May 1955 (Box 13)
  - Speech for Century Club (empty) (Box 13)
  - Lecture for M.I.T. Architectural Seminar, 7/13/60 (Box 13)
  - Terrace Plaza - Cincinnati (Box 13)
  - Lecture Notes - Foreign Service Officers School, 2/27/59 (Box 13)
  - Lecture for College of William and Mary, "Power, Taste & Class" - April 26, 1957 (Box 13)
  - Speech for AAA - April 26, 1963, White Sulphur Springs, Va. (Box 13)
  - Speech, "What's the Matter with American Taste" (Box 13)
  - Speech for Herald-Tribune Book & Author Lunch, Nov. 30, 1954 (Box 13)
  - Speech for Institute of Architects - Philadelphia, April 16, 1951 (Box 13)
  - Speech - University of Michigan - Conference on Higher Education, Nov. 20, 1956 (Box 13)
  - Lecture for Philadelphia Library, April 16, 1959 (Box 13)
  - The Taste of Our Time, Lecture, Boston Museum of Fine Arts for the Institute of Contemporary Art, March 8, 1955 (Box 13)
  - Talk for Berkshire School, May 1955 (Box 13)
  - Speech for Bancroft Awards - Columbia University - April 23, 1957 (Box 13)
  - Speech for Elizabethan Club (Box 13)
  - The American Roundtable, May 22, 1957 (Box 13)
  - Saga of Man's Search for a Place to Sit Down (Box 13)
  - "The Writer and the City" (Yale, speech, April 1952) (Box 13)
  - TV Dec. 28, 1958, CBS "the Year Gone By" (Box 13)
  - Bergen Lecture, Yale, March 1958 (Box 13)
  - Bermuda Diary 1950 (Box 13)
  - Letters from Sinatra, July 1965 (Box 13)
  - European Journal - Spring 1960 (Box 13)
  - Untitled (Box 13)
  - Untitled (Box 13)
  - The Domesticated Americans II (Box 14)
  - The Tastemakers manuscript (Box 14)
  - More Than Meets the Eye (Box 14)
  - Art-Makers (Box 14)
  - Cain, Wacker O (Box 15)
  - C/A Miscellaneous 1981 (Box 15)
  - Bach, Ira J. (Box 15)
  - Buechner, Tom and Freddy (Box 15)
  - Berkshire Art Association 1967 (Box 15)
  - The Berkshire Eagle (Box 15)
  - Brown, Milton & Blanche (Box 15)
  - Brown, J. Carter (Box 15)
  - B miscl. (Box 15)
  - Atheneum Publishers (Box 15)
  - Adams, Frederich B., Jr. (Box 15)
  - Allen, Federal Lewis & Agnes etc. (Box 15)
  - American Art Journal - 1974 (Box 15)
  - Abramovitz, Max & Anita (Box 15)
  - Adelman, Bob (Box 15)
  - Askew, Pamela (Box 15)
  - Ayrton, Michael & Elizabeth (Box 15)
  - A misc. (Box 15)
  - Addresses (Box 15)
  - ARTnews 1987 (Box 15)
  - Gramercy Park 1989 (Box 15)
  - Arch Digest (Box 15)
  - A.D. Tearsheets '87 (Box 15)
  - American Academy in Rome (Box 15)
  - A.A.R. Registration (Box 15)
  - AAR Pub. Com. (Box 15)
  - Arch. Digest 1987 (Box 15)
  - American Academy in Rome 1984 (Box 15)
  - Archives of American Art (Box 15)
  - Glenway - Wescott (Box 15)
  - Wheeler-Wescott (Box 15)
  - Wadsworth Atheneum - (Gaddis) (Box 15)
  - Weil, Wendy Weil (Box 15)
  - Wohl, Hellmut & Alice (Box 15)
  - Warshaw, Howard & Franny (Box 15)
  - The Wilson Quarterly (Box 15)
  - Warranties (Box 15)
  - W miscl. (Box 15)
  - X,Y,Z miscl. (Box 15)
  - Yale (Box 15)
  - Vassar exhibit of R.L. photographs (Box 16)
  - Vassar Art Gallery (Box 16)
  - Very Long Letter to Liz - notes and index (Box 16)
  - Venice '76 (Box 16)
  - V miscl. (Box 16)
  - U miscl. (Box 16)
  - T miscl. (Box 16)
  - Thorne, Mary Jean (Box 16)
  - Pryce - Jones (empty) (Box 16)
  - Shipman, Mrs. Arthur (Box 16)
  - Sox, David, 1986 (Box 16)
  - Sargeant, Winthrop & Jane (Box 16)
  - Smithsonian Institution (Box 16)
  - Society of American Historians (Box 16)
  - Szarkowski, John (Box 16)
  - Smith, J. Kellum, Jr. (Box 16)
  - Sotheby's (Box 16)
  - Stein, Donna M. (Box 16)
  - S miscl. (Box 16)
  - Shipley - resignation (Box 16)
  - McAndrew, John & Betty (Box 16)
  - McIver, Loren (Box 16)
  - MacDowell Colony - 1979 (Box 16)
  - MacDowell Colony - 1978 (Box 16)
  - Mc miscl. (Box 16)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, visiting committees, etc. Bryant fellows (Box 16)
  - More Than Meets the Eye (correspondence) (Box 16)
  - MOMA - RL MS miscellaneous (Box 16)
  - Museum of Modern Art (Box 16)
  - M miscl. (Box 16)
  - New York Historical Society (Box 16)
  - No. Egremont (Box 16)
  - Noguchi, Isamu (Box 16)
  - Olana (preservation corresp.) (Box 16)
  - Osborn (Box 16)
  - Hartford (Box 17)
  - Hyland, Jack & Casey (Box 17)
  - G miscl. (Box 17)
  - Guggenheim Museum (Box 17)